Look.
Further down the line now.
Bring up the next load.
The future!
VENDORS SHOUT
CHILD: Throw us a penny!
INAUDIBLE
Here's your bag.
Is it Doctor Lydgate?
Yes. Welcome to Middlemarch, sir.
I understand you've purchased
Dr Peacock's practice. Yes, I have.
You'll be kept busy! This way.
We're late. Let's go back. >
BABY CRIES >
Dodo, we're going to be late!
Thank you, Pimble.
I believe I shall give up riding,
Celia.
Dodo! Horses need exercising,
and Pimble needs employment!
Yes, I know, but is that all
we can do -
exercise horses
and employ servants?
Well, I don't know, Dodo.
Fences cost money, you know.
They'll cost a lot more
if you let 'em rot.
I think there's a middle way, Roach.
The cattle are getting out.
Whatever you want, we have!
Now, look at these beautiful
pig's trotters.
Come along, sir!
All made this morning!
Lovely fresh Middlemarch pies!
MAN COUGHS
WOMAN: He needs purging.
Shall I move him downstairs
and have him bled?
No. It's relieving to the spirit
to be active,
but in these cases, we can only
watch the fever's progress.
I'll look in again tomorrow.
Lydgate! How are you?
Reverend Farebrother! Well enough.
Finding your feet? I feel
as if I've been here all my life.
Good. Old Mrs Hislop has tales of
this place in the old days
that would make your blood run cold,
Lydgate.
I doubt it. Doctors aren't easily
shocked. You see all sides of life.
I ran into a friend of yours.
Trawley was the name.
I knew him in Paris.
A political idealist.
He wanted to found
a utopian community. Did he do it?
I think not. He'd been
a doctor at a German spa,
married his richest patient
and retired before he was 30.
More a REALIST than an idealist!
What a shameful waste of a life.
Not everyone has your moral fibre.
I'm late for a christening.
Will I be forgiven? I doubt it.
Mr Bulstrode.
Ah! Good day to you, Mr Farebrother.
Dr Lydgate, will you do me
the favour
of walking over to the bank
with me?
The plans for the new hospital are
ready for your inspection. Are they?
Good! Of course. Excuse us.
When will it be ready for use?
A matter of months. Excellent.
And I can assure you it will be
dedicated as a fever hospital.
I've advised that it should.
Is that the new saw-bones?
Yes.
Well spoken of. Clever man.
Good family, too, they say.
An excellent design, Mr Bulstrode.
The architect has vision,
and he's been well instructed.
In a few years' time, we could have
a first-class medical school here.
Why should London have it all?
The causes and treatment of typhoid
and cholera
will soon yield
to scientific investigation.
Why not here in Middlemarch?
Aye. Where are the kitchens?
Oh, I see. Good, good.
You will continue to give your
services without payment? Of course.
I have my general practice.
I know I can do good here.
My aim is to do good small work
for Middlemarch
and great work for the world.
You see, I am ambitious.
I am glad to hear it, sir.
As you know, I mean to entrust to
you
the superintendence of my
hospital.
You recognise the spiritual
interests in your patients?
Of course.
This room could be a laboratory.
I refer to the chaplaincy.
I propose that Mr Farebrother
is replaced
by Mr Tyke.
Oh? What's wrong with Farebrother?
Oh...he is a man
deeply painful to contemplate.
I suppose there is not a clergyman
in England who has greater talents.
Really? I haven't yet been pained
by finding any excessive talent
in Middlemarch!
He dissipates his talents.
He lacks spirituality.
He brings his calling into
disrepute.
Indeed? I have no knowledge
of these matters.
If this were a laboratory...
Dr Lydgate.
The chaplaincy will be referred
to the board. You will have to vote.
I trust I may ask of you this,
at least -
in virtue of our association,
which I look forward to -
that you will not be influenced
by my opponents in this matter.
I confess to you that the affairs
of this temporal world
are nothing to me
when they are in conflict
with my spiritual duty.
I trust I make myself clear.
I'm not sure I've made
the fireplaces big enough.
"Farm workers' cottages -
a new design."
Very nice, but you know Uncle.
They'll never be built, Dodo.
Might we look through
Mama's jewels now,
and divide them between us?
It would be lacking in respect
if we never looked at them.
And Sir James Chettam and that other
gentleman are dining here tonight.
Mr Casaubon.
Uncle says he is a most learned man.
What about Mama's jewels?
You would like to WEAR them?
I thought we BOTH might.
Look.
Wear it with your Indian muslin.
Dodo, I thought this cross for you.
Not as a trinket! You have it.
Have them all.
How can I wear ornaments if you
never will?
I cannot wear trinkets
to keep you in countenance!
They are lovely, though.
You know, it's strange how deeply
colours seem to penetrate one.
Like a scent.
They look like fragments of heaven.
Here's a bracelet to match it.
Try it, Dodo.
They are lovely. And necklaces
are quite usual now, really, Dodo,
even for Christians.
There must be women in heaven
who wore jewels.
Keep these, if nothing else.
Perhaps I shall.
Sir Humphry Davy, now...
I dined with him years ago.
Wordsworth was there, you know.
The poet.
Davy was a poet, too, you know.
Or, as you might say, Wordsworth
was poet one, and Davy was poet two.
Wordsworth was poet one,
Davy was poet two!
D'you know Davy, Casaubon?
No, sir. I regret that I do not.
Chettam studied Davy
and his agricultural chemistry,
but it won't do.
I am reading it, Miss Brooke,
because I want to take one of my
farms over
and set a good pattern to
my tenants. Do you approve of that?
Yes. Very much indeed, Sir James.
I wish my uncle would do the same.
No, no!
Fancy farming!
Most expensive whistle you can buy.
May as well keep a pack of hounds.
Surely it's no sin
to spend money on the land.
Ladies don't understand
political economy.
A little light literature
is more suitable.
Uncle! Novels, you know.
Poetry - Scott,
Shelley.
Southey.
Do you know Southey, Casaubon?
I have, at present, little leisure
for... modern literature.
I live too much with the dead,
perhaps.
Casaubon's engaged on a great work,
aren't you, Casaubon?
I believe I am, yes.
Perhaps too great a work
for the mind of one man to compass.
May I know what it is, Mr Casaubon?
I'm compiling a key
to all mythologies, Miss Brooke.
I am seeking to elucidate
those elements
which underpin every system of
belief known to man.
Not a subject of great interest
to young ladies.
On the contrary.
It is a wonderful endeavour.
You're very kind, Miss Brooke.
I'm much encouraged.
How do you arrange your documents?
Pigeon-holes, partly.
They won't do. I never know
whether a paper's in A or Z.
Let me sort them, Uncle.
I would letter them all and make a
list of subjects under each letter.
An excellent secretary!
I hear you're determined to give up
riding, Miss Brooke.
Surely it isn't true.
It is, Sir James. Oh, but why?
You're such
an accomplished horsewoman,
and it is healthy exercise.
Every lady should be a horsewoman,
that she may accompany her husband.
Surely you don't think horseriding
is wrong. I think it wrong for ME.
Why? I feel there should be
a better way to live.
But, surely...!
We should not enquire too closely
of motives.
I understand Miss Brooke.
Thank you.
There is so much that is trivial
about our lives. I'm so ignorant.
My education has been so imperfect.
There's so much to do.
So much to learn.
You're truly interested
in scholarship, then? Oh, yes!
It must be wonderful to be engaged
in some great work, as you are.
It is a great challenge to... bring
together all the major disciplines -
theology, philosophy, cosmology,
to show how every faith springs
from the same ultimate source.
It is a great endeavour.
My notes present a formidable range
of volumes, but the crowning task
is to condense
these still-expanding insights
into a unified whole. Yes!
Miss Brooke...
..this visit, for me, has been...
May I say this?
..more than pleasant.
I have felt the...disadvantage
of...loneliness
that inevitably accompanies
any serious scholarship.
But the presence of youth,
of cheerful companionship...
Perhaps I've said too much.
No, not at all.
I feel I understand you.
And if I say that I've longed for
some great purpose in my life
that would give it shape and
meaning...
..you do not find
such an aspiration ridiculous?
Surprising in one so young,
but not ridiculous.
No!
Not ridiculous at all.
It is time for me to leave.
Yes, of course.
Now, then. A good journey to you,
and, er, a safe one.
They'll take you a good crack.
Well, well. He's not
such a bad fellow, after all.
LAUGHTER FROM INSIDE
Eighty-nine!
Luck of the Devil, Mr Farebrother! >
Lovely player! He could've made
a living at it.
He DOES, near enough!
It pays for his butter,
if not his bread! >
Vicaring don't pay.
I don't blame him.
APPLAUSE
Mr Farebrother!
Found another lamb to fleece,
Mr Farebrother? >
More fool you, Mr Fred,
for playing with a clergyman!
Clergy always wins.
God's on their side.
So He is, Mrs Dollop!
Thank you.
Master Vincy! >
Here.
I can't afford to pay you yet,
Mr Bambridge.
I'm not surprised!
I hope I shan't have to talk to your
father about it.
Mr Farebrother! Your winnings.
Oh, good!
Good evening.
Evening, Mrs Dollop.
Evening, Mr Farebrother.
Lydgate!
Well met!
Are you busy? Where are you off to?
A solitary supper. There's an
experiment I want to think about.
Postpone it. Come and take supper
at my house. I insist.
You can inspect
my collection. What do you say?
Goodnight, Camden, dear.
Goodnight, Mother.
Goodnight, all.
Formidable!
You're a scientist.
I keep my mind alive.
You have no hobbies? There's much I
want to achieve in my profession...
..practically and in theory.
I have the ocean to swim in here.
Many would call this a backwater.
It's ideal for me. I want to work
on fever - prevention and treatment.
I can show dramatic results
in a small town.
By example, I want to bring about
a general reform in practice.
We shouldn't be selling panaceas
that are as useful as ditch-water!
You'd like to make Middlemarch
a model for all England.
That's exactly right!
In the country you can follow your
own course. People let you alone.
Hmm. Lydgate,
I think I should warn you...
You're new to Middlemarch.
It's not the simple place it seems.
For example,
you're my friend, I hope,
but if you vote for me as chaplain,
you'll make an enemy of Bulstrode,
and that is something no-one should
do lightly. He can do you harm.
I hope I act on my beliefs,
not out of petty expediency.
Life's too short for that sort
of provincial moral shabbiness.
What does he have against you?
That I don't teach his opinions,
which he calls spiritual religion.
It's the sort of Christianity
that makes people feel
uncomfortable, not better.
It makes me shudder!
And he says I haven't time to look
after both hospitals. It's true...
..but I could MAKE the time.
I should be glad of the £40.
I should be happier to earn it
in the exercise of my vocation,
rather than at billiards or cards!
But let's dismiss all that.
If you do vote with Bulstrode,
you're not to cut me in consequence.
Idealism and intelligence
are thin on the ground here.
I simply can't afford
to do without you, Lydgate.
Thank you, Pritchard.
Knock at Mr Fred's door
and say it is half past ten!
Yes, Mrs Vincy.
Mama, when Fred comes down,
don't give him red herrings.
I cannot bear the smell.
Rosamond, a red herring's not much!
Women must put up with things.
If it's only the smell of a herring,
you are lucky.
You'll be married one day.
Yes, but not to anyone like Fred,
or anyone who has herrings!
NO-ONE from Middlemarch.
You've refused the pick of them!
Mama, I wish you would not say
"the pick of them".
It is a vulgar expression.
Yes. Very likely, my dear.
What SHOULD I say?
The BEST of them.
That sounds just as plain and common
to me, but you must know, dear.
Morning, Mother, Rosy.
Rosamond!
Ham, toast, potted beef.
Is there nothing else, Pritchard?
Should you like eggs, sir? Eggs? No!
Bring me a grilled bone. Yes, sir.
What would you think if I came down
and ordered grilled bone?
That you
were an uncommonly fast young lady!
You are disagreeable! "Disagreeable"
describes your feelings, Rosy!
It describes the smell
of a grilled bone. No.
It describes
certain finicking notions
acquired in finishing school.
I shall ride over
to Stone Court. Oh?
To see Mary Garth.
YOU should see your uncle
more often, Rosy.
He wanted you to live with him,
and now Mary Garth has got in there!
It was either that
or become a governess!
I'd rather NOTHING was left to me
if I must endure him
and his ugly relations.
You cannot afford to be proud.
Your uncle is fond of you, but he'll
leave you NOTHING
unless you are agreeable.
His horrid relations are camped out
in that parlour, night and day,
like carrion crows!
The least you could do is go and see
him. He's not long for this world.
Very well, Mama. I'll go with Fred.
I'll even sing Ye Banks And Braes
for the 137,000th time,
if my uncle requests me to.
Mama says that there is a new doctor
attending Uncle.
Lydgate. Clever fellow.
I see! What do you mean?
Now I know why we're going
to Stone Court! Fred!
Dammit! I wish I had a decent horse!
There, there. Never mind, Sugar.
Come on.
# Ye'll break my heart,
ye warbling birds,
# That warble on
# The flowery thorn... #
HE COUGHS
# Ye mind me of departed joys
# Departed
# Never to return. #
Very good, missy! >
Just like a little blackbird.
What would SHE know of departed
joys? Not much, I hope!
THEY LAUGH FEEBLY
Fred, come here.
Be off with the lot of you. I've got
a bone to pick with this boy here.
That's it. Sit close. Good boy.
Now, then...
A little bird tells me
you've got into debt
by playing billiards for money.
And this same little bird tells me
that you've been borrowing
on your expectations.
You tell folk that I'm leaving you
my land,
and raise cash
on the strength of it.
Indeed I do not, sir! Bulstrode,
the banker, tells a different tale.
Then he's mistaken, sir, or
he's lying, or your LITTLE BIRD is!
I can alter my will,
and I shall,
unless you contradict the story.
I HAVE contradicted it, Uncle!
Yes, but I want documentation
from Bulstrode,
saying, clearly, that he hears
nothing against you in this respect.
Beg Bulstrode?
A gentleman shouldn't ask it!
Suit yourself. There are plenty
of others I can leave my money to.
Aye! Money's a good egg...
STARTS COUGHING
Here, Mr Featherstone.
That's it. Drink up.
You're a good girl, Mary.
You've got a plain face and a sharp
tongue
and I daresay you'll never
get a husband,
but you're a good girl.
The best girl I know!
IS she, now?! Did you get the books
I sent you, Mary? Yes, thank you.
Why do you want books?
Because I'm fond of reading!
TOO fond!
You have the newspaper to read to
me. That's enough.
I like to read to myself, as well,
and I SHALL.
You shall NOT! I can't abide seeing
her read to herself. It's unnatural.
You mind not to bring her any more
books. Do you hear?
Yes, sir, I hear.
Ah! My little blackbird.
We haven't had Home, Sweet Home.
I'm sure everyone thinks I've sung
enough. I'll sing it next time.
I may be in my coffin next time!
Oh! Oh...!
Home, Sweet Home, if you please.
THEY WHISPER
# Mid pleasures and palaces
# Though we may roam... #
HE DRONES ALONG
# There's no...
# There's no place
# Like home
# Like home. #
SHE PLAYS CLOSING CHORDS
Very pretty. Very nice.
Ah! Here he comes, at last. >
The man of the moment! Dr Lydgate,
my niece, Miss Rosamond Vincy.
How do you do, Miss Vincy?
I'd heard Miss Vincy was a musician.
I hadn't expected so much talent.
Best in Middlemarch, >
I'll be bound!
Middlemarch is not a high standard.
We must be leaving.
I told Mama... Fred?
Where is my whip? Oh.
Thank you.
His uncle is a baronet.
There was a Lydgate at Oxford
who spent no end of money.
But rich men may have
paupers for cousins.
It always matters
to be of a good family.
Did Mary say anything about me?
Yes. She said she thought you were
very unsteady,
and that if you asked
her to marry you, she'd refuse.
Well, she might have waited till I
DID ask!
What do you see in her? She's
not a girl to fall in love with.
How would YOU know
what men fall in love with?
Did she really say that?
I always tell the truth.
She's right. I am unsteady.
But I do love her, Rosy.
Oh, Lord! Now I must get Father
to butter up Uncle Bulstrode.
Mmm.
Miss Brooke!
Morning, Lucy.
Can I have some of these? Of course.
Could you look after Monk, Ben?
Morning, Mrs Barnacle.
Morning, Miss Brooke.
How's your husband?
Still bad, Miss Brooke.
May I come in? Very honoured, Miss.
BABY CRIES
PAINFUL COUGHING
WHEEZING BREATHS
Give him some of that jelly.
The room's damp.
I told Mr Brooke about the roof.
I shall remind him again.
Thank you. It's very good of you.
Miss Brooke!
I was on my way to see you.
I have a little petitioner for you.
What is it?
A little Maltese gentleman.
I'm sorry,
but I cannot bear toy breeds.
I should be terrified of treading
on it. My eyesight's rather poor.
Well, well, no matter.
John, take this.
DOG YAPS
Can't stand the things myself,
but they tell me ladies like 'em.
May I walk with you? Yes, of course.
It's terrible that we live in ease
while our tenants rot in pig-sties.
We deserve to be beaten out of our
beautiful houses
with a scourge of
small cords! You think THAT? Yes.
You have your own opinion
about EVERYTHING, Miss Brooke.
Do you know, I...I envy you that.
Lovegood was telling me that you've
made a plan for new cottages.
He was full of praise. They will
come to nothing.
Uncle won't consent
to anything that costs him money.
It's shameful.
Miss Brooke, I should like to
consult your plans if I may.
I am determined to build
new cottages at Freshitt.
How very good of you, Sir James.
Nothing would please me more.
How wonderful it would be
if we could set a pattern
about here.
He's setting a BAD example!
The cottages are madness!
Of course, he's a rich man. He can
afford his follies,
but he should
think of the consequences to others.
We shall all end up out of pocket,
I make no doubt.
Well...so be it.
I shall go over to Lowick
and ask Casaubon to dine again.
Oh, no! Mmm? Oh, well, perhaps not.
Yes, yes, carry on.
I hope you'll invite Mr Casaubon
as often as he's willing to come.
Dodo! One can be sure of intelligent
conversation. What of Sir James?
He would do anything you wish.
He is a good creature.
More sensible than anyone imagines.
I suppose you know
he's in love with you. Celia!
Anyone with eyes can see that.
He loves you,
and thinks you return his affection.
Why? I never agreed with him about
ANYTHING but the cottages.
I had to tell you.
You went on as always -
never seeing what is quite plain
to everyone else.
I must have no more
to do with the cottages.
I know it's your favourite fad...
Fad?! Do you think I only care about
people's homes in that childish way?
How can one be nobly Christian among
people with such petty thoughts?
DOOR SLAMS
Vincy, I stretch my tolerance
towards your family
because you are my wife's brother!
As for your son, Frederick,
it was entirely from worldly vanity
that you sent him to university.
Now you are reaping the reward
of your own folly.
There's no going back!
It's a good British feeling
to try to raise your family
a little!
It's my duty to help my son! Do you
mean us to come down in the world?
I am not sure I should be
befriending your son
by helping him to acquire
Featherstone's property.
If you only want SAINTS
to have money,
you must give up
some profitable partnerships!
That's all I can say!
Trying to play bishop and banker
makes a man's name stink!
Vincy, it was not your prudence
or judgement,
but my material help
that has enabled you
to keep your place in the trade!
I like to be master.
I can't deny it.
We're family.
We must stick together.
If you won't stop these rumours,
you may as well slander him
yourself.
I'd consider it...
..unhandsome of you to refuse to
write this letter,
brother Bulstrode.
I'd consider it very unhandsome.
"..And I distinctly affirm...
"..that I have no information
that your son...
"..borrowed any money
on any property
"that might accrue to him
on Mr Featherstone's demise."
Accrue! Property! Demise!
Fine words for a speculative man!
Come from nowhere, that one, too!
Mind you, I hear he owns your father
lock, stock and barrel.
Or his BANK does.
What do you expect now? A fortune?
There we are.
There...
..and there...
..and there...and...
..there.
That's all.
You might show a little gratitude.
Thank you, sir.
I'm very much obliged to you.
Yes! I should think you are!
Mary! Am I wanted?
No. I came to see YOU, Mary.
What's the matter?
Mary, you'll think
I'm a despicable fellow.
Uncle Featherstone
has given me £100.
£100?!
Yes.
It's very generous. I am grateful,
but I was hoping it might be more,
because I'm in debt for £160,
and a friend - a very GOOD friend -
has signed a bill of security
for me,
taking on the whole sum!
I was hoping Uncle might clear it,
and then I could start afresh.
You see?
I confess everything to you.
That makes everything better? No!
You looked so sad
when I came in just now.
It's a shame
you should stay and be bullied!
I have an easy life compared
to some.
I tried being a teacher,
but I wasn't fit for that.
My mind's too fond of wandering.
I can't be a clergyman.
I never said you SHOULD!
There are other sorts of work,
aren't there?
Oh, Fred! Why can't you resolve on
something sensible and stick to it?
I'm good for NOTHING if you don't
love me.
My father says an idle man
shouldn't exist, let alone MARRY.
Then what am I to do?
Blow my brains out?!
No. On the whole, I think you'd do
better to pass your examination.
Mr Farebrother says it is
disgracefully easy.
Everything's
easy to HIM! I could pass.
I'm ten times as clever
as some of the men that pass.
Then you must be ten times as IDLE!
But if I passed, you wouldn't want
me to go into the Church, would you?
It's not what I want!
What do YOU think?
I know that if you won't give me any
encouragement, I shall get WORSE!
I can't give encouragement to a man
who gets into debt and won't work!
What news have you brought, Uncle?
News about what? The sheep stealer.
Were you not at the assizes?
Oh, yes. Poor John Bunch.
It seems that we can't let him off.
He's to be hanged. Uncle!
There's nothing to be done.
Let's go inside.
There's a sharp air.
I feel it, driving.
I came by Lowick.
Talked with Casaubon.
Saw his library
and that kind of thing.
He greatly enjoyed his visits
here over the last few weeks.
Yes...
Yes, Uncle? Ah, well...
He seems to have a high opinion
of YOU, my dear.
A very high opinion indeed.
The fact is,
he asked permission
to pay his addresses to you.
I told him you were very young,
and so forth.
I had to tell him there
was very little chance, you know.
But I had to promise the poor
fellow that I would speak with you,
so there you have it.
I am very grateful to Mr Casaubon.
If he makes me an offer,
I shall accept him.
That's very well...
..but, Chettam, have you not thought
of HIM? He is a very good match.
Our lands lie together,
and I believe that Chettam, too,
wishes to marry you. I mention it,
you see.
It's impossible that I should ever
marry Sir James.
If he thinks of marrying me,
he has made a great mistake.
I should have thought he was
just the sort of man a woman liked.
Please do not mention him in that
light again.
Casaubon, now...
Well, he's a good match in some
ways. He's a clever man, a scholar.
I never got anything out of him,
any ideas.
However, he's a tip-top man.
May be Bishop.
But, you know, he's over five and
forty, and his health's not strong.
Marriage can be a noose, my dear.
You're fond of your own opinions,
but a man likes to be master.
I only mention these things to you.
I don't want a husband
of my own age.
He should be above me in judgement
and experience, knowledge.
I know I must expect trials.
I've never thought of marriage
as personal ease.
I admire and honour Mr Casaubon
more than any man I ever saw.
Well, my dear...
..that being so...
..I have a letter for you
from Mr Casaubon here in my pocket.
Yes, here it is.
"My dear Miss Brooke,
"I have your guardian's permission
to address you
"on a subject than which I have none
more at heart.
"From the first, I discerned in you
a rare combination of elements
"uniquely compatible
with my own needs -
"elevation of thought
and capability of devotion,
"allied to graces of sex
beyond all my hopes.
"Had I not made your acquaintance,
I might well have gone to the last
"without any attempt to lighten my
solitariness by a matrimonial union.
"To be accepted by you as your
husband, my dear Miss Brooke,
"would be the highest of
providential gifts.
"In return, I can at least offer you
an affection
"hitherto unwasted."
Uncle says
Mr Casaubon is dining again.
I hope someone else is there
and I shan't hear him eat his soup.
What's so remarkable about
his soup eating?
The way he scrapes his spoon!
Don't make any more observations
of that kind.
Why not? They are quite true!
Many things are true
which only the commonest minds see.
Then common minds are useful.
If his mother had a common mind, she
might have taught him better! Celia!
It is right to tell you, Celia,
that I am engaged to marry
Mr Casaubon. Oh, Dodo...!
I hope you will be happy.
I beg your pardon if I said anything
to hurt you.
Oh, never mind, Kitty. Don't grieve.
We should never admire
the same people.
Casaubon!
Good God, it's horrible!
It's very vexing.
What business has a shrivelled
old bachelor to marry a young girl?
He has one foot in the grave!
He's taking it OUT!
Apparently, she says he has a great
soul.
A great bladder for dried peas
to rattle in!
It does seem most unfair.
Brooke ought not to allow it. He
should insist on it being put off!
Brooke only insists on not spending
money! Horrible, Mrs Cadwallader!
It IS!
I don't think of myself.
..Not entirely.
I think of HER.
I throw her over. With you, she
might have become a sensible woman,
but now I wish her joy
of her hair shirt. Very perverse.
Very perverse indeed.
However, Chettam...
..if I were a man...
..I think I should prefer Celia.
Celia?
I think you'll find she admires you
as much as a man expects to be
admired.
She is a sweet girl.
Very fond of geraniums.
More docile than her sister,
though not quite so fine a figure.
I think I should prefer Celia
if I were a man.
Oh, dear.
After you, my dear.
Here we are then.
Welcome to Lowick. Thank you!
Well, it's a good old house,
you know.
Decent proportions.
I went into all that once -
Palladio and so forth.
It's all a bit dark and bare
at present.
Bachelor's house, of course.
Bachelor's house.
This is my library.
As you may well imagine, a great deal
of my time is spent in here.
And these are my notebooks...
..for my OWN work...
..The Key To All Mythologies.
I think I should begin
to learn Latin and Greek, Edward.
I could read to you, as Milton's
daughters did to their father.
Those young ladies regarded
that exercise in unknown tongues
as a rebellion!
I hope you don't expect ME
to be rebellious, Edward.
Latin and Greek...
I fear it might be rather wearisome
for you.
It would be a great advantage if you
could copy the Greek characters,
and, to that end, it might be very
well to begin with a little reading.
QUOTES CLASSICAL GREEK
"Education is a possession
which none can take away."
It would only take a very little,
you know. Lighter colours, perhaps.
What do you think of duck egg blue?
Everything is as I would wish it.
I am delighted to hear it, my dear.
Now, favour me with an opinion
of the room I have planned
as your boudoir.
Oh, yes! Well!
This could make a pretty room
with some kind of new hangings,
a sofa or two, that sort of thing.
It's rather bare now. Uncle, don't
speak of altering ANYTHING. Oh.
Was this your mother's room, Edward?
Indeed it was.
And this...
..is your mother.
And who is this?
Her elder sister.
The sister is pretty.
It is an interesting face.
You never mentioned her to me,
Edward. No.
My aunt...made an unfortunate
marriage. I never saw her.
Shall we walk in the garden?
Who's that youngster
sketching over there?
A young relative of mine.
The grandson of the lady
whose portrait you noticed -
my Aunt Julia.
Oh!
You're an artist, I see!
No. I only sketch a little.
There's nothing fit to be seen.
Oh, come now!
My cousin, Mr Ladislaw.
Will, Miss Dorothea
and Miss Celia Brooke. How do you
do? How do you do, Miss Brooke?
Mr Brooke.
This is a nice bit...is it not?
I did a little myself
in this way, at one time.
Did you know THAT?
Oh!
This is what I call
a nice little thing!
Done with what we used
to call brio, mmm?
I am no judge, Uncle.
I can never see the beauty
of pictures that are praised.
It is a language I don't understand.
Well, there we are.
You'll come to my house
and I'll show you what I've done
in this line. Thank you.
Well, shall we walk on?
What's that young man
going to do with himself, Casaubon?
Is he going to be a painter, or
a poet? He has the look of a poet.
Shelley had that look in his eyes.
The answer to your question, sir,
is painfully doubtful.
My cousin is many things,
but nothing in particular.
To be more charitable, he has not
yet found his vocation.
His present purpose
is to travel abroad.
To what end, I do not know.
Culture, he says. I have agreed
to support him for a year or so.
He shall be tried
by the test of freedom.
Arabella, my dear!
Brooke has invited half the town,
as well as the county!
What a to-do! He was never one
to spend money like this!
There's Bulstrode, the banker,
and the new sawbones, Lydgate.
LADY CHETTAM: One hears well of him.
He is a gentleman,
but I can remember when medical men
knew their place -
with the servants.
Hicks, for example.
He was butcher-like,
but he understood my constitution.
This is too much! Brooke is asking
us to sit down with tradespeople!
Middlemarch bag-men! There's Vincy!
The ribbon manufacturer!
Well, I'm quite happy to peruse
his pattern book,
but I don't want
to eat my dinner with the fellow,
or his awful wife! It'll be some
whim of Brooke's. He means well.
I'll tell you what he means.
He means to go into politics and
stand for Parliament!
And as a Liberal!
That's what all this
is got up in aid of -
toadying to the hoi polloi!
Friends, a few brief words
on this happy occasion.
We celebrate the betrothal
of my dear niece, Dorothea,
to my good and learned friend,
the Reverend Casaubon,
and to share their happiness.
Marriage, you know,
is a joining, a union,
a sort of closing up, d'you see?
And yet, in another sense,
it's a reaching out, an exploration,
if you will,
and so forth...
Progress. Well, that is going to
happen, whether we like it or not,
and that's why I am for it.
That's why I welcome
progressive men.
Er... men who have the well-being
of their fellow men at heart,
and women, too, of course!
Here's Mr Bulstrode,
of the bank.
You're very welcome, sir!
And Mayor Vincy...who, er...
Excellent! Yes.
And Dr Lydgate, who studied
in Paris.
All the new ideas
for the new hospital.
Progress, d'you see?
Progress and reform.
But in a spirit of temperance
and moderation.
Let it never be said that Brooke
was NOT for progress and reform.
Excellent!
Yes.
I forgot! Ladies and gentlemen,
I give you the toast -
the happy couple!
ALL: The happy couple!
CHATTER BREAKS OUT
My thanks again, sir.
A most delightful occasion.
I'm fond of my nieces. Fonder than
I can say.
I've tried to do my best
for them since their parents died,
as far as a bachelor can.
Nothing means more to me
than that they should be happy.
You intend to extend
your wedding journey as far as Rome.
The weather will be mild, and there
are manuscripts in the Vatican
which will be invaluable to my
research.
I long to see the antiquities.
Edward can tell you all about them.
I shall not detain you longer.
We shall meet again very soon.
I still regret that your sister
is not to accompany us.
You will have many lonely hours.
I shall feel constrained to make
the utmost use of my time in Rome.
I should feel more at liberty if
you had a companion.
More at liberty?
If you had a companion, I could put
you both in the care of a cicerone,
and we would achieve
two purposes at once.
You misunderstand me, Edward, if you
think I should not value your time.
Please do not refer to this again.
Please don't be anxious about me.
Very well, my dear.
As you wish.
I can't hold it...! I can't be
expected...! Continue to sponge him.
He's holding his own.
Is it cholera?
It's a fever, but it isn't cholera,
I assure you.
Your children are all well?
Yes, thank you, sir.
D'you see? It's broke again! >
I wish he could be more comfortable.
When the new hospital opens,
we'll be able to treat fevers
of all kinds.
But your man will be himself again
long before that. That's my opinion.
Thank you, sir.
All right.
READS SILENTLY
KNOCK ON DOOR
Good morning, Doctor.
You asked to see me.
Ah, yes, yes. I did.
I was wondering if you'd come to
a conclusion about the chaplaincy.
Is that all?
It is of great importance to me
that the spiritual care of the
patients
be given to a man worthy of
the charge.
Will you support me
and vote for Mr Tyke?
I don't know Mr Tyke. I'm sure he's
a worthy man, but so is Farebrother.
He's done unpaid duty long enough.
I am a doctor.
I have no opinion on such matters.
Then I earnestly advise you
to FORM one, Doctor.
A great deal may depend on it.
MUSIC AND LAUGHTER
Delicious, Mrs Vincy!
Enjoy the cards.
We will!
Is this the first of your parties
the Doctor has been to? >
Yes. Yes, it is.
I daresay you're used to far grander
parties, but ours are just as jolly.
You can't be serious about Tyke! >
Oh, no! Not for ME!
His sermons are nothing but
evangelical doctrine. Eh, Lydgate?
You get no cant from Farebrother! >
He'll sit down to whist
with ANYONE. >
- How will you vote, Vincy?
- Not on the board now. >
However I voted,
I'd be offending SOMEONE.
What do YOU think, Dr Lydgate?
I know very little of the case,
but appointments should not be made
on the basis of personal liking.
If you want reform,
sometimes you have to pension off
all those good fellows.
Hang your reforms! Humbug!
What's wrong with good fellows?
There's not enough of them!
Mr Farebrother, you've done again!
Farebrother's won again!
Every time!
What do I owe you, Fred?
Five pennies, Mrs Plymdale.
Lydgate.
Are you avoiding me, having decided
to vote against me?
I haven't decided on my vote, but
I'll never cut you.
Sometimes I feel I shall starve for
want of intelligent conversation.
Still, first things first. Here's
the serious business of the evening!
Have a game of whist.
Oh, Doctor, please!
Thank you, no. No?!
You're not the serious man I took
you for! You're too light for this!
Now, what's trumps?
Dr Lydgate. Miss Vincy.
You must find us dull in
Middlemarch.
When I think of how we must seem
through your eyes,
we must seem very stupid.
You have lived in Paris.
I have only been once to LONDON.
I'm just a raw country girl.
You call yourself
a raw country girl?
Well, I pass at Middlemarch, but...
..I'm really afraid of YOU.
I take Middlemarch as it comes.
You have nothing to fear.
I've found some charms
that are greater than I expected.
The rides towards Tipton and Lowick?
Everyone is pleased with those.
No. I mean something
much nearer to me.
I do not believe what you have done!
You plunderer! You thief!
You've ruined me, you have!
Mrs Plymdale...!
BULSTRODE: 'Farebrother is a man
deeply painful to contemplate.
'He lacks spirituality. He brings
his calling into disrepute.
'..A great deal may depend on it.'
INAUDIBLE
Do you have time, Edward? My dear,
my work has led me to neglect you.
I have set aside today
for your diversion.
Not today.
This site is regarded by many as
one of the finest on the continent.
Rome is among several cities
to which an extreme hyperbole
has been applied -
"See Rome and die."
In your case, I would make
an emendation -
"See Rome as a bride, and live
thenceforth as a happy wife."
I thought you might like to visit
the Palazzo Doria Pamphili.
Would YOU like to see it? It is
highly esteemed by the cognoscenti.
Yes, but do you CARE about it?
I'm ready to go if you wish it.
Are you not tired, Edward?
My dear, as I said, today is for
your diversion.
Fatigue is neither here nor there.
Edward, I do not need diversions.
I love to visit the antiquities,
but only if YOU enjoy it, too.
I would be far happier if you would
let me help you with your research.
Most persons think it worthwhile
to visit the Palazzo Doria Pamphili.
The great family
which created the collection
reached its peak
in the 17th century,
when their son came to the chair
of St Peter as Innocent X.
The god, Apollo, or Phoebus.
I suspect of the Augustan period.
The cult of Apollo is linked
to that of Bacchus
and inspired the appalling excesses
of the Bacchanalian revels.
Note how the male and female
principles are combined.
The ancients believed
that this combination...
..served as an inspiration
to the arts and music.
Look at this, Edward.
A common theme
in Athenian sculpture.
Probably an inferior copy
of a Greek original.
Perhaps we've seen enough
for one day. Shall we go?
I believe we are very near
the Capitoline Library.
I wonder if you might allow me half
an hour to consult some documents.
Of course.
Why didn't you say so before?
There's much here of great interest
for you. A half an hour then.
GERMAN ACCENT: Look at this woman!
Beautiful.
I should like to paint her
as the Madonna.
Good God!
Do you know her?
I do.
She's...married to my cousin.
She's married? But I saw her with
some old Geistlicher! Who was he?
The father? The uncle? Her husband.
Introduce her to me, Ladislaw!
I must paint her! Confound you,
Naumann! I'm not so brazen as you!
MAN: Well, I go for Farebrother.
Put £40 in his pocket and you'll do
no harm.
He's a good fellow, without
too much of the parson about him.
Oh, indeed, Mr Hawley,
for he spends half his days
in the Green Dragon
playing billiards for money!
Mr Tyke is a real gospel preacher.
It would be against my conscience
to vote against Tyke.
Vote against BULSTRODE, you mean!
I beg your pardon, sir?!
Good afternoon to you!
Am I the last?
No. Our chairman, Mr Bulstrode,
hasn't arrived yet.
Nor his protegy,
the uniquely talented Dr Lydgate(!)
Why should one man have this town
in his pocket
just because
half the town owes him money?
Good day, gentlemen.
Good day.
Oh. I see we are not yet
all assembled.
Nevertheless, we meet today,
gentlemen,
as directors
of the board of the hospital,
to appoint a chaplain.
The issue is between Mr Farebrother
and Mr Tyke.
The qualities of each are known to
us all,
but if anyone wishes to speak...
Ah, yes, well,
Farebrother and Tyke...
both excellent men in their way...
you know...
And a chaplain with a salary...
I believe that Mr Tyke
is everything he should be.
How's that?
Apostolic and so forth, you know?
I'm sure we're happy
to vote for him.
You've been crammed, Mr Brooke.
What? What about Farebrother? He has
been doing the work without pay.
MURMURS OF ASSENT
If pay is to be given, it should be
given to HIM!
I call it a confounded
job to take the thing away from him!
ALL: Hear, hear!
Yes, well, Farebrother... Yes...
BULSTRODE: Excuse me.
Mr Hawley,
Mr Brooke has been fully informed
of Mr Farebrother's character.
Yes. By his enemies!
I take it there is no personal
hostility here.
I'll swear there damn well IS!
Perhaps we should vote now.
Please write the name
of your candidate.
Ah! Here's our man.
Apologies, gentlemen.
Well, gentlemen,
I perceive the votes are equally
divided at present. Dr Lydgate,
would you write your vote, please?
Well, THAT'S settled it!
Damned scandalous!
You speak
with some peculiar meaning, sir!
I expect you to vote
with Mr Bulstrode, that's all, sir.
Do you find that offensive?
It may be, but I shall not desist
from voting with him
on THAT account!
Mr Tyke is hereby elected
to the post of chaplain.
Ah, well, there you are.