Still in Yorkshire, eh, Jess?
Look at the wee'uns egg hunting.
Rather them than me.
Oh!
I'm so sorry.
Watch where you're going.
I'm very sorry. I...
took my eye off for a second.
Oh, blast it.
Put it on the list.
Sirop glicosilada.
Sirop...
It's so bloody hard to put things
back with the labels facing out!
Salammoniac, small.
Udder ointment, two tins.
Percolate of mercury.
Wait. Can you spell that, please?
Oh, and some more absorbent gauze.
Six dozen rolls should do it.
Absorbent gauze. Six...
Would you mind?
I have an awful lot to get through.
What if I do mind?
KETTLE WHISTLES
You know that sound
means it's boiling, yes?
They are saying
we dropped more bombs
than all the German raids
on London in The Great War.
Well, sounds to me like
they don't need you after all.
I should withdraw my name,
if I were you. Very funny.
Where is Mrs Hall?
Out with Gerald maybe.
PHONE RINGING
You're welcome.
I suppose you want me to get that?
I never thought I'd admit this,
but we are missing Tristan.